hello herbie
nice to see you again and i think the
last time we met in person was in a
auspicious place in delphi in greece
quite
amazing wasn't it extraordinary
experience yeah really unique
conference so i don't think i've ever
been at the gathering quite like that
really nice to to catch up a few
tragic things have happened since then
like the world's a different place um
but i'm also um remembering your friend
nam i'm spacing on his name um the
wonderful friend of yours who was really
young
i was really sad to hear that yeah yeah
he was an amazing guy
yeah he was a songwriter and he was
really committed to
all his energies went in to try and help
with the help of environment
initiatives and we started something
called artist projectors some
15 years ago to try and raise money from
rock music
as a project so that was quite a success
but sadly that's uh what we're going to
continue but obviously
is fundraising capacity is now no longer
there you know
[Music]
so that that project was you did cover
versions of
famous songs and then donated the
proceeds from those yeah
kenny wrote a famous song called under
the boardwalk in the late 60s
and uh you know still lived off the
royalties from that song to quite an
extent
but 30 years ago he decided
to do to devote all his energies to
produce rock music
versions of versions of songs
by famous rock artists and basically to
use that music to raise money from
environmental projects
first of all we had something called the
earth love fund
then we 15 years ago we started another
one called
artist project earth yeah so we funded
some
between those two organizations about
700 environmental projects around the
world
wonderful so kenny took
rock songs by you know sting or youtube
or
coldplay or you know all these guys and
then added new uh
backing tracks with cuban or african uh
music
to them and that was really remarkable
stuff that he that he did kelly was an
amazing wonderful guy
so he died about two weeks three weeks
ago
yeah i know a little bit about that work
through may east who is part of the
she's a trustee as well yeah sure but
um normally with these conversations
that i call
voices of the regeneration i i'm always
really
um like honored really to
to have elders like you um join this
series
because you for me
i mean you've been busy with this for
what
50 years um yeah 45 years something like
that yeah
he knew schumacher you were yeah in all
those early meetings um
i mean i started when i was a student at
the london school of economics
and i decided in the
mid early 70s to study social
anthropology
because i've been living in notting hill
gate
surrounded by people from all over the
world for many years and i decided
i need to know more about cultural
cultures that have continued for eons of
time and
the people in notting hill obviously
represented in some ways
cultures from africa from india from
bangladesh from
sri lanka and so on and so forth so i
wanted to understand better
you know how people have been living for
all these many many
millennia and you know so that was my
entry point into trying to
study social anthropology and that
really led me to then
become an environmentalist because it
became clear that the cultures that
these people came from were
sustainable or indeed regenerative
cultures
and basically could have continued
indefinitely if it hadn't been for the
interference by western society that was
really my entry point and then
in the mid 70s i met satish kumar
in london and wrote an article on the
very first issue of resurgency ever
edited in 1973 called the radial house
which was basically
designed for an ecological house solar
powered house so that was quite
pioneering stuff i suppose in those days
and so
from then on i really worked in this
field ever since
but the really interesting experience i
subsequently had was
i was working with john seymour do you
know the name john seymour yeah of
course i actually
just be before we got on i dug out his
self-sufficiency handbook
um and but i thought that he
you co-authored the book with him didn't
you but not this we did we
did a tv series together it's an amazing
project
we approached the bbc uh to see whether
they might be interested in a tv series
on the history of human impact on the
planet
and eventually we managed to get the the
budget together
with co-productions from germany and
austria and elsewhere
and it became a seven hour tv series for
bbc two
both far from paradise and in that
series we basically traced
the impact of mainly western
civilization on the environment starting
actually not just western but when we
started in iraq with
actually no in anatolia the very first
villages agricultural bridges
uh twelve thousand years ago
then we filmed in iraq one of the
very earliest big bigger cities in
mesopotamia
and the very impacts on the environment
that that came out of
urban lifestyles at that time basically
causing desalination of farmland or
surrounding
surrounding the old city
i always i always find sorry to
interrupt briefly but then
it fits very well here i always find it
quite telling that the
oldest written record of humanity the
epic of gilgamesh
tells the story of downwind
desertification it basically says
do not cut down the trees otherwise um
mesopotamia will run dry
and we never learned the lesson well we
quoted gilgamesh of course in the
program also there are these clay
tablets
in which they recorded the annual yields
of crops from the surrounding
countryside and gradually they went down
and down and down first
the wheat yields went down then the
barley yields went down and
and so on and so forth and what was the
reason for this well it turned out to be
salinization of soils basically water
for irrigation that had some salt
content and never flashing
that salt water out of the fields so
gradually
subsidizing the soils feeding or
not as a result causing that city
ultimately to decline and ultimately die
it's a fascinating thing to look at in
this series
how would you because i mean you're
really talking to to kind of
the beginning of the problem um with
yeah
with us becoming
agriculturalists and city dwellers
in terms of like for me more and more
i'm realizing that
while it seems like a um an
oversimplification if
the old wisdom that seems to be common
of
all indigenous cultures that we belong
to the earth rather than the earth
belongs to us that we are patterned by
the land
and by life's processes that we're quite
literally expressions of it
and and fundamentally dependent on
the health of that that process yeah
that seems to be
where we went wrong but do you think it
was directly linked to becoming
farmers and um and city dwellers or
where did that come in well i mean as
you know i mean we were hunter-gatherers
for
you know hundreds of thousands of years
basically only
harvesting from nature and always just
taking what was available from nature
and then when agriculture first started
obviously it was
the first stage of a major manipulation
of nature where basically say okay i
have a bit of land here that i grow my
crops in and
that's my land and that is where i need
to get my
my food from
but then there was a conceptual and
systemic problem that basically
you can't harvest from nature and not
give back to it i mean
or from a piece of land and not give
back so the question of how to keep that
land productive and fertile was became a
major major issue
early on and certainly you know the
story of woo and
on other early towns and in places like
mesopotamia
are a demonstration of that certainly
agriculture
is also of course if you like the the
fall from
from from grace in some ways you know
adam and eve
if you if you take that story they were
basically hunter-gatherers
and once you get into agriculture you
have to start manipulating nature as
never before
that causes all kinds of conflict
between humans and nature but also
ultimately
the jealousy of people seeing wealth
accumulating
from you know the sort of intense
utilization of nature
and wanting some of that themselves and
the kind of
kind of tribal wars or wars between uh
tribes
who live in adjoining regions and see
the wealth of
of a newly built city and so you know
the
conflicts between humans and nature are
directly related to the early stages of
both agriculture and urbanization but
it's it's interesting that
that what we now find out more and more
is that the
what what in that frame would be called
pre-agricultural societies
were actually practicing just a much
more sophisticated form
of um
farming or um
stewarding uh the landscape being really
keystone species
in in their interventions like for
example what's pretty clear now is that
most of the colombian rainforest um
is a forest garden that evolved through
human intervention and with human
intervention but humans as nature so
similarly in so many other places the
north american indian
planes the the herds of buffalo they
weren't quite
naturally the way that i mean that
it's precisely this false dualism of
nature and culture that
that that runs through the even the way
we talk about it
but but in many ways
the north american ecosystem before
like pre-columbian and
pre-colonialization
was also a dynamic ecosystem in which
human beings
were through fire stick burning
and animal like keeping wild herds of
animals
um were interfering
where would was that shift to that
more primitive form of agriculture with
which then also came this idea of
this is our land like i sometimes wonder
whether the ownership of land
and that switching perception of rather
than belonging to the la is
actually more fundamental than than the
agricultural start what do you think
well i mean certainly i mean early
agriculture was
much more collective than than modern
agriculture so i mean land typically
was kind of not not owned by individuals
but it was kind of
utilized by tribes and the tribes
certainly you know by
particularly referring to north america
and south america i mean
tribal agriculture is basically uh
still involves give and take between
humans and nature i mean the
cultivation of crops depended very much
on utilization of
soils uh to ensure that that could be
done on a continual basis i mean in
south america
it was particularly slash burn
agriculture
where you you know remove a bit of
forest and then
burn burn the sticks and then use the
ash for cultivating the crops and then
after a couple of years
the forest comes back and the trees we
grow and
the fruit trees that you may have
planted then become
also harvested by by the animals by the
monkeys by the birds
and so on and then you move on to the
next piece of land i spent a lot of time
making documentaries in the amazon in
the late 80s and
so certainly i worked with a wonderful
man called daraposi
and with the kaiopo in in south america
and brazil
and they he was one of the first people
to document the point that you've just
made which was basically
the amazon rainforest was very much a
place
it was not a natural forest in the
strict sense of the world but
they were everywhere you look there
islands of palm trees for instance which
were always an indication that people
have lived there
and there's also the traces of very well
maintained very rich farmland you know
that that has been found there was a
fascinating documentary made a few years
ago by the bbc
as the forest is cleared by cattle
ranchers and and then
soybean growers suddenly you know
circles and squares emerged out of this
cleared forest
and it was clear that that land had
already been cleared
on a much smaller scale way way you know
in centuries ago and they often left
some very rich soils behind was called
terra prata it's kind of
an indication of that they were very
good at kind of manipulating the
fertility of the land through
putting back manure but also fish bones
and and
you know other types of biochar they
were they were actually
biochar yeah all of that was kind of you
know it's recently been demonstrated
yeah this is a fascinating story i mean
certainly
the history of agriculture is very
complex it's not always just
taking bits of land for a group of of
tribal people and
and excluding nature from it as even
then you know there's often a give and
take between
humans and nature and in forms of
cultivation
but people are still partly
hunter-gatherers and partly farmers
and what what in your in your
life's journey what began the focus on
cities i mean i i remember reading in
2001 2002 when
briefing on the work that you've done on
the on the ecological footprint of
london
and yeah you've been very involved with
london when you're also involved in
setting up the carnival
in nottingham not not setting up but uh
i moved to notting hill in in the in 60
1964 coming
coming from germany you know having
decided to study in london for for for a
few terms at
london university but then i very
quickly changed
track and basically became a community
activist in nautical gate
at the store in the portobello road and
lots of
crazy stuff going on at that time and
yes i became involved in
helping to run the nottingham carnival
in the late 60s and
yeah i mean as i already briefly
mentioned you know i encountered all
these people from different parts of the
world that were all living together very
peacefully
in that part of north london uh west
london and
so i it became occurred to me that we
need to understand
you know i became fascinated by
understanding london
as a huge organism because london was
the first
modern city of a million people plus
from the 18th century on
18th century onwards and then grew into
a city of
8.5 million people by by the start of
the second world war so it was
an unique example of of urban growth of
a kind that had never been
had never occurred before in human
history and i tried to understand
how that growth might have occurred
obviously the direct linkages between
between the development of steam
technology
and london as a center of a global
empire all this kind of stuff
but then i started to kind of see
you know where all over the world cities
were
in one way another copying that sort of
growth and
by the time you know by the by the early
seventies there were
dozens of cities across the world
already of a similar size
so i began to think about what is the
impact
of that urbanization on on the natural
world
and at that time i started to think
about what people later started called
the ecological footprint
of of of a big city lag lana where does
the food come from where does the timber
come from
where does the water come from where all
the resources that people take for
granted
and never really think about on in their
daily way of life
than us and i read a brief
essay by an american guy called wollman
who had written about the metabolism of
cities i've come up with that concept
some years before and i thought it would
be interesting to try and
quantify the resources that flow into
london and
and quantify the amounts of waste coming
out the other end and then
from that also quantify the actual land
areas that are required to keep london
going
and that was kind of i suppose fairly
pioneering work at the time this was 85
i think it was
so 95 1995.
and then i started sorry was this that
was actually
matis vacanade and the official kind of
yeah yeah methodology
okay well i wrote it i started i wrote
an uh an
essay called metabolism of cities in 89
i think it was
uh and this beginning to look at the
contrast between
the way nature works as a circular
system basically
nature cannot exist and continue to
exist without continuously
re-fertilizing
itself as it were i mean if you go into
forest
in the autumn and see the leaves fall
you know that this is
the basis for next year's growth whereas
if
you go into a city you never take that
into account basically you take
resources so never mind what happens to
the waste
so we started to conceptualize or
differentiate between linear and
circular systems
in this essay i wrote in 89 i think it
was
and that partly i have to say came out
of the work we did on this tv series far
from paradise
but just another example of what we
looked at in that series was the impact
of rome on north africa i don't know
for about uh 500 years rome
also at that time a city of about a
million people
kept you know supplied the bulk of its
food from from north africa
which had been tamed by by tamed if you
like
by by julius caesar and other uh
roman generals and basically they turned
a forest landscape similar to what you
can still find in places like kenya
today acacia far is full of animals
zebras lions tigers
elephants lions and basically
you know cut down the forest
crated up many of the animals and put
them up against the gladiators in rome
and elsewhere and then turned
the land into farmland so for about 500
years
they got about 500 000 tons of grain
from north africa
that went into the stomachs of romans
then the sewage ended up in the
mediterranean
fertility was never returned to the land
of north africa
you know there was a permanent legacy of
the
lifestyles of romans in this lineage
fashion
taking resources without returning the
waste back to the land
so that was kind of like a prototype of
what i
then saw in london two thousand years
later if you like
briefly i i remember always remember
this that when i was um
14 years old my father who um had a real
passion for deserts um it took me
to southern algeria we we drove through
tunisia into algeria
and then down to taman raset and through
the um
atlas not the atlas mountains the the
hogar mountains
over a region called um the tassily
plateau near janette
which is the south um eastern
yet southeastern corner of algeria and
in there
in this plateau there are lots of
canyons and in the canyons are um
you can find beautiful caves yeah yeah
and oasis and cave paintings and and the
cave paintings
which struck me after driving with my
father
2000 kilometers through the desert
including a place called the
the garden of satan which was one of the
hottest places in the sahara
and then arriving in a place where the
cave paintings
depicted crocodiles giraffes lions
and hippos and in every direction
it was two and a half thousand
kilometers of desert
and and so it's just another example how
the romans continued a process that that
um
at points um in prehistory
most of north africa was was um very
much like
sub-saharan africa in terms of exactly
yes i mean
similar forest cover and similar
vegeta you know fauna as well yes so
you know the the romans were crated up
all these animals and
you know thousands and thousands ended
up in in the coliseum and another
in a similar kind of arenas in the roman
empire yeah
shocking story so i mean in some ways my
interest in the
metabolism of cities didn't just come
from
living in london uh at that you know
in the 60s early 70s but also from
having
been involved in this tv series apart
from paradise for the bbc and
you know documenting the impacts also
at the plateau wrote about the
deforestation of attica
in his critia's dialogue saying how that
landscape forest landscape on the
outskirts of athens
you know obviously 500 years before rome
had also
led to the deforestation and permanent
damage to the environment
as a result of the demands uh for
resources made by assange
on its surrounding countryside and and
they had
pretty ruthless ecological war
strategies the way that the romans after
they finally subdued cathago they
actually spotted the soils
they they brought in salt and and
distributed salt on
the fertile soils of catago in order to
really but subsequently they also
you know use that as farmland for
feeding the romans
as well yeah anyway so certainly you
know there's a difference
in the world which is primarily
agricultural and villages and small
towns and and the world that we live in
today
i mean we as you know we now live in a
world where
more than half the world's population
live in cities and we have over 20 mega
cities of up to 15
20 billion 20 million people and so
their consumption patterns now
affects what we are doing to the planet
as never before
i've just written an article for the
college's website
on the linkages between deforestation in
in the amazon and uh and chinese demand
for meat
i don't know that story it's
extraordinary
you know as a result of the growth in
wealth
you know and economic growth in china
and
urbanization meat consumption in china
has gone up from seven kilos per person
to
10 times at about 70 kilos over the last
40 years
but at the same time they've paved over
a lot of their farmland
to urbanizations through building
motorways and all the rest of it
so now where does the where do the
animal feeds come from to
chinese population well primarily from
from mata grosso and from the amazon
yeah from from argentina and some of it
from
from north america but eight eighty
percent of the
soya beans now produced in the amazon
region
go to eat pigs in china you know it's an
extraordinary story
but another aspect of sort of ecological
footprint
of modern urbanization you know i mean
you you've spent the last at least the
last 30
20 years 30 years um researching city
and seeing that evolution of
um of these new mega cities
um i mean basically when you were
starting this work on london
how many cities about above ten thousand
are there ten million people were there
in china
and how many are there now it's just
mushroom
it's absolutely astonishing i mean just
it's an amazing story and the
interesting thing is i mean i filmed in
in china we did another tv series
uh in 1998 which was
uh called uh people's planet and we
filmed in shanghai and at that time we
could still see
a lot of agriculture being conducted
within the city itself
of small agricultural plots within the
city region
and then the surrounding countryside was
about
cultivated basically for the purpose of
feeding shanghai
about 300 000 hectares of land on the
edge of shanghai at that time still
being used
to provide vegetables and and so on to
shanghai but all of that is largely
paved over now and so
when they have they are beginning to
revive urban agriculture particularly
for vegetable crops but when it comes to
grains and animal feeds
they go long distance they go global now
and
i mean how do after all this research
practice because i always remember like
when we're in delphi you
you shared the story of your work as
thinker in residence in melbourne and
how
melbourne adelaide yeah yeah adelaide
adelaide in australia
are you still hopeful for cities
to have a chance to really to be
redesigned and do you think that there
are cities that are simply too big not
to fail
um and and then the issue because the
early kind of
schumacherian take on back to the land
and kind of two acres to spades
is also impossible with the amount of
people we have at the moment so
where do you sit with this issue of that
some of us will have to live in high
density areas and
and and how do we um make cities
regenerative well do you mention this
example of
adelaide so i was in 2003 i was
after having done all this work and
written a lot about this you know
problem a systemic problem between
urbanization and what we're doing to the
planet
particularly to world's ecosystems i got
invited to be a thinker in residence in
adelaide south australia
premier of south australia his name is
mike ran and he was a unique
guy he's no longer in that role but you
know he was an
unique guy because he
had been working for greenpeace in new
zealand
and he was reading you know they had
really internalized the
issue what we need to do to change the
way we
relate to the world's environment so
when he
got the job as running south australia
you know
as premier of south australia there was
a problem at the time of
the water supply to athlete which is the
city region of 1.2 million people
uh from the very sort of
bit of a trickle of a river called the
murray river which was drying up at the
time
so they were getting really concerned
cooked out the city region continued to
exist
so then basically out of this concern
about water supply they said well should
we have a look at the whole
system how the city works city region
works
so my job was basically to analyze
adelaide in south australia which is a
population of 1.7 million people in
total
from the point of view of sustainability
and so basically i
did this for 10 weeks you know endless
numbers of seminars and
and working groups with people from all
over the all over the city region
and ultimately produce the report with
32 recommendations
on renewable energy on water efficiency
on
on wastewater recycling on on
regeneration of organic waste in
form of compost uh on some ideas of
improving public transport and so on and
basically it was all implemented the
entire
32 month plan was implemented so it's
become you know
from a point of view energy for instance
it's over 60 percent of
energy electricity supply now comes from
solar and wind
they build the world's largest battery
in order to even out the
fluctuations of renewable energy this is
the work with tesla is it
yeah the tesla battery yeah yeah
100 of the organic waste is now returned
to local farmland there's still a lot of
agriculture on the edge of
on the edge of adelaide and in south
australia
uh water recycling uh
wastewater recycling for irrigation
purposes
and so forth so i mean it is an example
of a city region
that really has looked at itself and say
okay we can do things differently
in addition to being you know really
very sustainable in terms of its
resource use
uh or indeed regenerative because i mean
you know all these process
recircularizing the metabolism
of adelaide goes beyond sustainability
and so certainly uh it is a very
nice thing project you have been
involved in
but i've never been able to replicate it
i've not never had another opportunity
to do something similar elsewhere you
know so
i did a lot of work on london and we had
something called the sustainable london
trust
some years before that and we kind of
published reports about how london
would think of itself as a place that
could function very differently
also made a documentary for channel 4 on
london's metabolism
and we looked at the inputs of resources
into london
use of materials in london's economy and
then where do the waste stand up
but that was just before ken livingston
became
mayor of london but again i mean there's
a little bit of tweaking that has gone
on
but by and large you know cities like
london are so preoccupied with
their own wealth and their their their
power as financial
centers and a service economy centers
and so on so
it's very hard to get cities that are so
used to
taking resources from the rest of the
world particularly in the case of london
as
the heart of you know the british empire
and then saying okay
this could function quite diff so i mean
i certainly haven't seen
examples yet of other major city regions
trying to do something similar and i was
able to do
with my ground in in adelaide in south
australia have you ever done any work
with
um puran desai and sue riddleston and
the the buyer
i hope to get them going actually when
you know
bioregional yes i mean yeah
he used to come to my lectures in london
and yeah
but didn't didn't they um start a whole
network
of at least kind of suburb projects or
or
some like parts running these um
looking at this one planet or yeah i
know yeah yeah
yeah what do you think it's a it's an
aspiration basically you know
we see the beddington zero energy
development which they have to
get going or you know it's a wonderful
example of what one can do in in cities
but the architects
who who designed this he's a very good
friend of mine
bill dumpster bill dunster
yeah you've never been able to do
something on a similar scale elsewhere
either
but you know there's good examples
popping up from various places
mainly on a small scale sometimes
obviously there's a lot of work going on
on eco villages as well you know but
by and large as you said earlier on i
mean we have to find ways if you're
serious about living in an urbanizing
world
we have to find ways of making these
cities function very very differently
but how would you how would you see that
because on the one hand
of course the it's clear that we need to
produce energy food water as cl
close to home as possible in a way that
actually regenerates that resource
rather than depletes
it um but that's easily said
conceptually
and there's it's wonderful to like we we
see a
revival of urban farming in
in parks and in um yeah all of that yeah
wherever
they say same with some of the vertical
farming might
offer a little bit of additional food
production in cities
but um of course there it's always going
to be a balance in this
like re-regionalizing to what extent or
re-localizing at the city scale
and what's your sense um how
if we if we made that decision of trying
to close the loops as close to home as
possible
what percentage of the main consumptive
cycles could we actually relocalize 50
70 percent or well you have to
differentiate between various crops i
mean i think you can
not with vegetables and fruit crops and
obviously that
you know there's been a movement in that
direction for a long time i mean there's
a vigorous
global campaign on urban agriculture and
particularly of course with
poorer cities where food supply is
a serious issue where waste pollution or
particularly of organic waste
is a problem where people say okay why
don't we use
the sewage the the feces the animal
waste
for localized food production systems so
we're seeing a lot of that happen
in different parts of the world i had a
great time in havana cuba
some years ago where they were did that
very effectively
partly out of necessity of course but
that's another long story
but a lot happening with urban
agriculture when it comes to
when it comes to vegetables and some
fruit production and as you said
there's quite a lot happening now with
with vertical farming and so on
but when it comes to grains you see it's
a different story altogether
i mean when i did this study on london's
ecological footprint
which was which at that time i
quantified as being about 125 times
london's surface area roughly the
productive land of the uk
uh you know the fruit and vegetables are
not a very large part of that and in any
case
at the moment most of that comes from
spain from
america in in southern spain
which is huge areas of greenhouses
probably know
but when it comes to grains and animal
feeds we're talking about really very
large acreages 50
60 times the surface area of a given
city
that's where it's much harder to
relocalize that i mean
in the case of london historically when
they abolished abolish the
the corn laws in the mid 19th century
that was
kind of moved towards getting more more
and more of the grain
particularly the barley for bread
production
and also the animal feeds from north
america
from canada uh and from other parts of
the world
so i mean if you wanted to uh get
serious about london
supplying most of its grain again from
the uk you're talking about
much of the surface area of the farmland
in this in this country
but of course london has only got 12
percent of the uk's population
so you know where does bristol where
does birmingham get its brain from
but you're still talking about
territories else earth
in different parts of the world but i
mean obviously
there's a lot can be done if we are
serious about changing the way we do
things but for the moment
you know global trade and free trade is
still the name of the game
globalization has you know
intensified that development more than
ever
in human history so we are now you know
global exchange is what we are doing
in terms of food in terms of all the
other supplies so
we are obviously with britain going for
brexit it may be
may be interesting to see whether or not
there might be some change in direction
regarding food production but by and
large
we're talking still about you know the
game of global supplies
rather than relocalization but
what i'm trying to get is less the the
pattern
that unfortunately is still prevalent
but more
on the basis because you've also done
this work on regenerative cities with
the world future council and then
and published a book on regenerative
cities um
when was it 2015
14 and um you must have a
have a sense of if the political will
was there
if even
the business sector like the private
sector would say
we're willing to restructure how we
exist even the size
at which we exist into different
networks in order to refit the human
presence on earth and human impact on
earth
to the biophysical boundaries and create
um
more equity in the process like let's
let's assume
we'd say let's implement the donut in
cities like like kate rayworth is trying
to do it
now um what's your sense from having
looked at the figures for so many years
what is actually possible because of
course like we
we can relocalized food production but
then
there are all these other materials
streams where we
we are dependent on certain technologies
that we probably would want to use in
the future as well
maybe not as ubiquitously as we use them
now if
if the resource limit is such but but
how
how would you see that process and also
the
the link with cities with their region
because
if we're moving into the u.n decade for
ecosystems restoration right now
um what once we
look at the impact of cities which is
vast on the planet
um we also need to look at how to shift
that around and make
of course the demand of the city's the
driver
of regenerating and restoring the
ecosystem
well i mean obviously in in my in my
regenerative cities we
have about 20 case studies where various
ways people are trying to do that on on
on a limited scale i mean i obviously as
a it's already referred to i've got the
case study of
adelaide in there which is kind of
probably the most remarkable uh
turnaround that that you can probably
find anywhere but by and large
there are smaller niches of various
kinds underway now but
certainly you know the reality that
the urban urbanization is the
primary impact on the biosphere it's not
fully understood
i've been trying very hard to change
that people always point to economic
system as
their primary problem but not the actual
spatial
demands for land surfaces
and resources from elsewhere on the
planet made by
the uh by an urbanizing world
concept is still not very dominant i
think in the
debate i mean there's a lot of
discussion on the future cities there's
any number of organizations
that in one way another tried to deal
with urban sustainability
but there's eclair the international
council for local environment
initiatives or
the c40 initiative which brings together
some of the world's
biggest cities and half a dozen others
but by and large the understanding that
you know there's a conceptual systemic
problem between
an urbanizing world and the ever greater
impacts on the global environment
from the demand patterns of cities
difficult to bring that message home to
to thinkers so for instance just one
basic point is i mean we when london
grew in the 19th century so very rapidly
there was this huge problem about what
to do with sewage
so the thames was full of shit basically
and they said what can we do about this
and so they had
various consultants come to advise
london at that time
and so some people said well let's
recycle this stuff particularly a german
guy called leaving justice
let's recycle this stuff and put it back
on the farmland
and then keep farmland productive in
that way because
you realize that you had to return all
the nutrients contained in
which back to farmland in order to keep
it productive
that long story short they went for a
different approach which basically they
chucked the whole
all of it into the thames estuary not to
return it to the lamb
so then leaving said okay if we are not
going to return
the nutrients from london back to the
farmland we have to develop artificial
fertilizers
so that there's a direct link between
london's decision to go linear
in terms of its resource use
particularly plant nutrient
resource use and and you know it's
decision
to uh basically chuck this stuff into
the thames history instead
whereas today we have all the world
cities basically doing the same thing
but when you look at the world's major
rivers and the estuaries particularly
the
you know the large history such as the
mississippi for instance
so you have a large surplus of
fertilizers
from farmland and and dead zones is all
ending up
together causing dead zones
huge dead zones in estuaries so this is
a huge
conceptual problem the same thing is
happening with the yellow river with the
yangtze with the rhinest situation is a
little bit improved in recent years but
by and large
this conceptual problem and the
relationship between cities
they use the farmland their refusal to
to recycle the stuff and then at the
same time taking ever more farmland
to feed you know an ev ever more
meat-hungry
population so we are certainly you know
it would be nice to be
very positive and optimistic in this
respect
but for the moment we are not seeing
really serious
uh change in direction in in this
crucial
systemic context and
are you i mean one of my great
inspirations for thinking about cities
and and also
thinking about systemic
re-patterning particularly at the scale
of the region is sir patrick eddis and
the work that he did
in the yeah sure because he worked on so
many levels i mean
he was great he was he's got all these
uh these points were you know certainly
in his thinking yes
but not because he was on the one hand
he was a thinker but he was also a
practitioner the way that he
being professor at the university of
dundee um
actually moved into the slums of
edinburgh around the castle
and then worked with the prostitutes and
low lives to to basically begin a
process of gentrification he invented
the first
student union to bring the students into
that slum
area because he understood that when
they were there things would start
really okay he invented
the edinburgh festival by bringing
heckle and
and and people like kropotkin and all
sorts of
people to um scotland
with a clear because he had this
experience when he traveled
as a younger man in bavaria and got
served in a country um
country restaurant or country
and he was surprised by the level of
education of all the people
um working in that inn and and so he
really started this conversation in
scotland that really
led to a cultural blossoming of the
region and a
shift in the in the scottish education
um system like even the the celtic
revival he was also involved in that
bringing
the the myth of the old celtic legends
back into connection with scotland and
all of that mixed
with the art deco time and like the the
huge steel time
fascinating man and and i i want to read
up more about him i mean i obviously
read some of his work but not recently
so i'm glad you're reminding me of that
yeah
but i mean certainly i think your work
on on regenerative cultures i think is
also where i'm heading strongly to
because it's clear that you know it's
you know just looking at this sort of
physical metabolism of cities
is only one aspect of of the story that
we're talking about
yeah you see it needs to be internalized
deeply in the cultural context
in which we live and so i'm really very
respectful of what you're doing in this
context i think
i'm also with the club of rome and the
world future council we are
very much focused on cultural change
rather than just
the physical changes that are needed to
bring about the kind of
reconciliation if you like between
humanity and the global environment
so these are deeper issues beyond beyond
just the
physical metabolism of cities yeah
good that you mentioned the club of rome
i'm curious because you've been a member
of it for quite some time
and and even within the club of rome it
seems like there is
a culture shift happening right now from
what well i mean i know a lot of people
who are
involved with the club um and it and
there
seems to be a slow shifting away
from the legacy of a sort of
limits to growth everything has to be
computer modeled and very
data driven and and sort of
hard science driven to understanding the
sociological cultural dimension the
worldview dimension
the the fact that you can't make people
shift
by telling them what to to do but by
by actually recreating
like creating enabling conditions that
they that they
behavior changes because of a shift in
world view and a shift in understanding
can i just can i just stop you for a
second
[Music]
now it would be useful to know how to
edit this out there is a way of
pausing the recording let's try that
so yeah yeah so i mean obviously the
the club of rome's story is quite
interesting in his overall context
initially from the 1970s onwards with
limits to growth i mean that was a
fascinating study
you know computer model of what the
future is likely to hold
and certainly the collision course
between humanity and the environment was
starkly represented by by that work and
and
conceptualized and quantified for the
first time in a remarkable way
so certainly the club of rome if you
like the
for many years it lived off this glory
of that work
but also of the very controversial
nature of it because
the world's futurist hated
that there might be limits and so for
instance
herman khan in america was at that time
the leading
features he was one of the main
opponents
to the idea that there could be any
limits to progress to
this sort of march of civilization and
so on and so forth
so yeah for many years there was lots of
other reports written and
about particularly around this issue of
limits
but then gradually uh you know it became
clear that
one can solely concern oneself with that
particular perspective
so more recently you know there's a kind
of attempt to try to
bring in bring new dimensions into this
work and so certainly
cultural change in the deepest sense is
becoming much more important but also of
course rethinking economics i've been
heavily involved and work on reframing
economics
for the club of rome recently and of
course you mentioned the donut concept
of one of the members of the moment ago
so yeah there's a lot of thinking
underway i mean it is
but i mean it we have a strange
situation
the main author of the club of um limits
the growth report dennis meadows
together with his wife former wife
danella and she's
she's slightly no longer with us
basically dennis is now saying well it's
too late
we can all no longer expect you know a
reconciliation
ultimately between humanity environment
the impacts the pressures the
human numbers the demand on resources
if you add it all up together you know
you cannot imagine a scenario where
basically we can reverse
this collision course that we are on so
that's certainly obviously
quite a depressing perspective i'm not a
depressive
sort of guy really i always try to find
solutions
so yes i mean we are working on on
consciousness change
uh what could what could a new
civilization look like
we are working on as i said reframing
economics and particularly of course we
are concerned
and linking up with young people and and
you know these wonderful
young you know campaigners who are
saying okay
we do not accept that we don't have a
future
that we are going to have to pay for
your sins
like greater timber and so many of our
colleagues are now saying so that's
in some ways an incentive for the club
of rome
indeed also for the world future council
to say okay
you can no longer accept this deeply
depressing scenario that
comes from the work of some of the like
the forefathers of
of of you know the club of rome but we
are trying very hard to kind of try and
see whether or not we can come up
with positive perspectives but it's not
easy these days and i'm sure you are
healing of that yourself and your own
work when we are
really faced with very stark realities
in the world you know
human numbers multiplied by by you know
ever greater demand for resources
through
increasing living standards particularly
in developing countries or
positive along the country like china
obviously these are all factors
that we are trying to have to have to
get to grip with and it's not easy to do
so
no i mean it it the fascinating
situation is that
the only place of hope is actually to
some extent
beyond the frame of a linear data
analysis
um and modeling uh perspective of the
situation like they're
all wonderfully useful to have these
models
but um in many ways we now have to do
the impossible
because the likely and the probable
based on on scientific models
is literally unthinkable and
unconscionable
um so so we we we need to
somehow work miracles in
i think it's it's in the in the dual
path
of preparing
for the decades of the next three four
yeah the next three four decades um
in the holding the real possibility that
it is too late and that we need to
prepare for a very
climate unstable and and for many other
reasons unstable world
and but that the logical response to
that would still
be a trying to heal the place in the
region you're in
re-regionalizing production and
consumption to create more
redundancy and resilience built climate
resilience built the capacity for people
to um cooperate and collaborate in the
face of calamity
um as as a as a direct goal of political
policy
and which means re-regionalizing
political processes
it means all of that yeah sure economic
systems um
but in that i think is also the
potential pathway towards
the regeneration of patterns that would
then actually heal
both social and ecological systems to
the point that i still believe it's
it's possible to to some extent turn
back
the tide of cataclysm um and and
actually
um regenerate ecosystems because we have
so many
amazing examples of where where that has
been achieved yeah now of course i mean
i'm i'm
you work with john leo i think some of
the time but he's an old mate of mine as
well so yeah i mean
he's he's documented wonderful stuff
that's going on in china
you know and you know the reforestation
there in the yellow river happens
in ethiopia and elsewhere i mean a lot
of tree planting going on in ethiopia
uh yeah certainly i mean there's
wonderful initiatives on tree planting
in many places now
but then you see the pictures of you
know the burning rain forest and
and the the burning forests of siberia
and so on so
yeah you know we are busy in some places
of the world of some parts of the world
to replace lost vegetation
but then in others you know it's just
going up in smoke so yeah i mean i'm all
for
every possible initiative on
regenerating ecosystems obviously i mean
that's
for me you know the the main if you like
the gospel of the future
regenerative activities of all kinds
regenerative energy i mean it's great
what's happening with
it's renewable energy when it's
absolutely remarkable that we are now
seeing more investment
total you know annual capacity of
wind and solar than we are seeing in
coal-fired power stations and
gas fire process also all of that's
great but i mean it's certainly
difficult when you come to very large
urban systems like 10-20 million people
to power those with renewable energy to
get them to be
fully regenerative in terms of their
food supply so certainly
i mean in china they're talking about an
ecological civilization
which is quite a quite good thing but
it's all about china itself so they've
done a lot of replanting and
they're moving quite rapidly into
renewable energy but they're also still
building coal-fired power stations as
well
and they are i mean when you look at the
really big cities they are running on
on very large dams some of them for
instance the street gorgeous dam
chongqing powers parts of shanghai and
so
so that's all good stuff but at the same
time when you look at these enormous
global footprints
of a country like china particularly
when it comes to
animal feeds you know then you are
worried again and saying okay
i feel myself constantly in this sort of
balance of okay here are the
positive initiatives that are showing us
where we could go
in different directions globally uh we
are seeing all this stuff going on
also in the context of covet for
instance i mean everybody's suddenly
growing vegetables again you know which
is
great i mean you know a lot of friends
of mine who
for many years would just buy their
vegetables in the supermarket
suddenly growing vegetables again we
have even got you know set up on our
own plot of land here a few people who
wanted allotment you know say okay you
can have a plot here
on our few acres that we have and grow
your vegetables
all great stuff just whether or not that
can compete with the
global picture of where we are still
looking very different direction sadly
yeah no i i sense that it's it's
redesign but
not just on the supply side but heavily
on the demand side in the sense of
um that we actually open up a
conversation around
um quality of life and quality of human
relationships and the importance of
relationships
more than nature that that
leads to a redesign of how we live and
and what we want
and and our patterns both in terms of
diet and
other forms of patterns of consumption
but
i mean you mentioned the pandemic um
i'm i'm wondering whether also that that
trend that seemed so unstoppable of
um more and more people moving into
cities like certainly in
in india and in a number of places where
since the pandemic started
beginning to see a um reverse of that a
little bit of a reversal yeah
question that's that's a permanent
reversal of whether it's
just a temporary response here but yeah
that's certainly happening but in a
world where
where um periodic lockdowns
into your apartment or immediate living
space no matter how small it might be
for some
less privileged families um is is part
of
the new pattern that might happen more
regularly
i'm wondering um whether we
we're not going to see
a a new revival
of smaller village and
and smaller town living and
and also because through the pandemic
the
the hesitation to let people work from
home
has disappeared because so many uh
employers have to do it now
and in the process they they're
beginning to realize that that maybe
they don't need to have such large
offices and have everybody come in every
morning and
the masses um footprint of of
commuting might be reduced if people
only go to
the office one or two days a week and
work from home the rest of the time
or even with more people working
much further away from the central
office in
in small towns and villages um
yeah maybe maybe we're really seeing the
beginning of a deeper transformation
because also with regards to soils i
don't know if you've seen this but the
european union has just started a
program where they're
very much focusing on soil health as
essential
sure and aim for the next 20 years
well that's all good stuff and i mean
it's interesting
the way where we live now partly
resulted from what was happening in
london in the 70s
at that time we were faced with a very
major economic crisis and a huge
union you know sort of fights between
trade unions and government and
companies and so on blackouts and and
really i mean
it was an extraordinary time so there
was hundreds of thousands of people i
thought i moved out of london
ended up moving to where we went to
small holdings smaller towns villages
uh into mid wales and west wales into uh
herefordshire and so on it was a major
trend at the time there's no doubt about
it i mean
even a lasting trend i mean a lot of
people when you when i
speak to people around where we live in
south wales a lot of people at one point
lived in london
you know or certainly in bristol and
birmingham with bigger cities
and i mean certainly we are seeing new
opportunities as you already pointed out
i mean there's no doubt that more people
will be able to work more remotely than
they will be able to
able to do before similarly also global
travel i mean i think uh people have
realized that they can do zoom
conferences like we're doing right now
uh much more regularly than they they
were used to in the past so
yeah i mean you know when you look at
the skies you know
we have we are on the overhead route or
the route between
israel airport and the united states and
there's phallus airplanes
flying overhead yeah you know uh
four months six months ago so yeah i
think we're going to
certainly see some major trend changes
i think you're right about some people
in in you know india may be having
second thoughts about
you know living in villages rather than
living living in delhi or in mumbai or
something but
obviously it's all about having an
economic base you know and as long as
cities are magnets for people who who
want a better life
like you know china example of china is
demonstrates most vividly
then i think uh certainly it is not easy
to persuade people suddenly to give up
this
mirage of urban living that has been so
dominant
but yeah i mean it's certainly true that
you know whenever you have a cataclysm
of the kind
that we have right now with covet uh it
causes mind changes and causes cause
consciousness changes and is
to some extent uh going to have uh
result in different outcomes than we
would have expected
four or five months ago
[Music]
so if you were given
on the basis of your amazing track
record and
membership of um both world future
council and the club of rome if you were
given the opportunity to
advise um government leaders on
how to respond to um the pandemic and
how to spend the money that they're now
sp
spending anyway in order to restart
economies everywhere
um where would you put the effort
what do you think is the the main
place to really pay attention to um
education
food um urbanization a bit of all of it
um well i don't know whether you saw it
but i sort of
published a sort of postcode manifesto
did you see that did i say i did
oh yeah of course i wanted to mention
that
tell a little bit more about it because
i i actually i mean basically it's just
a checklist of where we need to go i
mean i did in 2003 i did
something called earth emergency call to
action
at that time that was for the
johannesburg summit u.n summit on
sustainability and
at that time it was already becoming
apparent that we are on a kind of global
crisis situation so basically
i took that document and brought it up
to date a little bit more
i'm saying basically you know it's all
about uh changes in direction in every
possible way
and i mean i've kind of done a new
version of that for the club around
which is specifically on economics
and reframing economics so basically
it's obviously all about circular
systems it's about
it's about understanding you know better
understanding the global impacts that we
have and
acting on those and i certainly think
you know that this kind of thinking is
is there in many people's heads these
days but there's a fundamental
difference
between between realization and actual
action to change and i think certainly
it's above ourselves the
financial systems i mean the willingness
of governments
to take control of economies it's not
really there at this moment in time
i mean it goes back to the end of this
cold war collapse of the soviet union
when basically the
world's governments were forced to
implement globalization because
companies wanted that and particularly
financial institutions
so it's really about power power systems
on the planet as long as we don't get
to grips with the fact that financial
systems demand
more growth regardless of the
consequences
that governments always cow towing at
this stage
to to the to the whims of companies and
their
globalization affects uh impacts or
or intentions
you know ultimately the power systems
that dominate what we do at the time
unless they change fundamentally we're
not going to get the change in direction
that we need
i mean we are seeing the incredible
dominance of a few
huge companies now you know really
running the planet whether it's oil
companies whether it's
global trading companies amazon being a
prime example
and we are seeing their their demands
controlling what we do and until we get
back to really
democracy in the real sense of the word
asserting itself with the
added a factor of young people
saying okay it's not just about do
decision making
for the next few years but for decision
making for the
next few too few centuries that have to
be
brought into the decision-making process
we're not going to get the change of
direction
i i mean there seemed to be like i would
love to be
play mouse in in a conversation like
like that i was just thinking within the
club of rome you have
um kate ray was his wonderful work on
donald economics then then you have john
fullerton who joined
bringing in capitalism then
for quite some time um bob costanza has
been part of the club with
more much more kind of um quantify
the worth of nature approach it has its
own pitfalls in it
and and some of them are involved in
this we all alliance this this
yeah that's right yeah yeah sure yeah
and where do you
because of course if we don't like from
a
systems perspective structure drives
behavior and we
like even those companies that aren't
part of the ones you just mentioned but
the
smaller but still very large ones that
really do want to change
are finding themselves hitting a glass
ceiling of what they can actually do
because the playing field is rigged
against
richard it's it's incentivized
incentivizes degeneration and the
externalization of
social and ecological damage um and
therefore
uh if we don't do this redesign
we won't be silly to expect a different
outcome
but do you really think that they're
moving towards some form of consensus of
how we could
i at least
in theory and later than also in
practice create a system that
um is regenerative by design in terms of
the economic system
like because they what what it's well
right now seems to be
the case is that on the one hand the
people say
it's impossible to be regenerative in a
capitalist system
actually there is something about the
ownership of the means of production and
the ownership of land that is
fundamentally structured in such a way
that that it creates this pyramid scheme
and then uh others who are more in a
sort of strategic way saying well
let's create regenerative capitalism
because they want to keep
the the arch capitalists and the current
dogma on board
and i i can see that there's wisdom in
both approaches
like trying to um redesign capitalism to
the point that what
what we end up with isn't capitalism
anymore but
use the language of redesigning
capitalism in order to keep people on
board
in the conversation about transformation
where do you
stand there um do you think we can save
capitalism or is it structurally
dysfunctional well it's not going to go
away that's
that's the reality of it i mean all the
revolutions that we've had in in
in the past have tried to get rid of
well not all of them i mean there's
always been the
you know the uprising of of the
workers the public against the power of
of the few
you know this has happened throughout
history and but sadly those people who
who had the
the reigns of power in their hand so far
still always won i mean look at you know
the
communist revolution in china or in
in in russia i mean basically in the end
both of them are now said you know state
couple or
you know capitalism has researched and
both both of those large
entities those huge countries sadly uh
and
the reality is that i mean it's
interesting to look at the
history of socialism and karl marx for
instance
was very interested in the metabolism
concept
realized that you know the concentration
of power by
by a few industrial industrialism
and money money men if you like
ultimately led to these conflicts
between humans and nature
so he argued that we needed to
understand
the relationship between in society and
nature in new ways and
referred to that in the context of the
metabolism of
societies but in the end
we are seeing now you know that the
dominance
of existing power structures have not
been broken
and so when it is great to conceptualize
new economics
uh donald economics uh human faced
economic well-being economics is being
done by many different people
but we don't have the rights of power in
our hands so i mean the
the real hope that i have is that the
pressure of young people
kids telling their parents around the
dinner table
that they cannot accept that they will
have to live in a world which is
totally where that you know
the indebtedness of young people to
as a result of externalities not being
internalized in the
price of products and so on is is a
given
so i think you know the realization
that we are on hiding to nothing with
modern civilization
in relationship to what we're doing to
nature that i think is the greatest hope
that we now have
i really think that you know the fact
that young people are
raising their voices so vividly and so
clearly and so lively
is where we can really put our sort of
you know put our hope more than anything
else
so i think it's great to have
alternative economies
coming up as concepts of the kind that
we've already talked about but
ultimately
unless there's a social pressure for
that generation for that change to take
place
then we are not going to get very far i
mean the socialist revolutions are
driven by by workers
and intellectuals but the
social movement today has not really had
any
really major sort of power to generate
change because there was no clear
force for change that was visible
whereas i think today with young people
saying
enough is enough we cannot accept that
we don't have a future
that to my mind is the greatest power
that we can hope will come we can really
generate
change in the world and and where do you
sit
last question with regard to um
that the transformation we're talking
about and still hoping for
in the context of contrary evidence
and then the hope of young generations
um maybe
finally tipping the balance towards
towards real transformational change
the i personally and i'm just wanting to
check
against your your um decades of
experience the
the the re-regionalization you mentioned
marks like kropotkin's mystical
anarchism
sure basically an anarchism that isn't
the what we now understand of anarchism
which is there's no rule
there's a radical subsidiarity that is
coupled with a level of education and
understanding
of the radical inter-being of life
that that would then make people without
the need for super natural
national and national structures of top
down
with where both national government and
international governance
become subsidiary to the enablement
of people in place meeting their needs
and and
also making decisions about how
needs are met in their place but in in
global solidarity that for me
this nested structure of refitting
ourselves
into life's nested processes where the
local
the regional and the global are
fundamentally
interconnected and interdependent is
is part of the pathway like bringing
really reinhabiting our regions
re-inhabiting
um well that's certainly something that
i mean working with john cena all those
years ago of course that was our main
issue our main concern you know local
regional self-sufficiency
self-reliance and so on but we still
have a long way to go over that i mean
just yesterday i was
watching a tv program on the bbc country
country farm it's called
and it showed how crops are currently
harvested
and this in this particular incident was
it was grass you know
silage and you saw these vast tractors
that could cut another more on each side
than one at the front they could cut
12 meter widths of of of grass right and
then they had these incredible machines
putting it all into uh into trainers and
then ultimately into
big plastic bags where the stylish was
being kept i'm saying all this is
because
i've been working a lot on the concept
of what i call the amplified man
we are so amplified by by technology
today
that for instance when it comes to
farming you know a village where where i
live today
used to grow in fact historically grew
out of the local
countryside it became possible for that
village to exist
because the people in the village at the
farmland on
around the village available to grow
their crops and them to
develop their their nice local
lifestyles
today villages in europe i completely
detached from
from the local countryside because
farming and the village
life no more i haven't got any direct
connections any longer
so until you get to the point where
people basically say okay
we will reconnect the lifestyle of the
of the region to the to the land even in
terms of how people participate
in food production so then i think we
are still
you know living in a sort of illusion i
mean basically
you know in the f in the past you know
20 30 of people used to farm the land
in britain today in europe today it's
about less than one percent of people
everybody who farms the land sits in a
huge tractor
has huge machinery available to them to
basically
you know farm three or four hundred five
hundred acres and i mean when you look
at that
in in the amazon and and in some places
where
today animal feeds are produced you know
one farmer can
farm five thousand acres you know with
these enormous machines
so we have a problem in terms of how we
are so amplified by technology
that we are not able to simply say okay
let's go back to
relocalization of the kind that helena
and albacore and others
have been talking about for for so long
the reality is
this contradiction between who we've
become as human beings
amplified through technology and how we
can get back to a way of life
that relates closely to where to to to
do the local countryside you know so
what i'm saying is
it's great to have this concept of
relocalization
and i'm very much part of that movement
and i grow my own vegetables and
i live you know on fire we get firewood
from the forest and
we have a close roasted community in our
village we do festivals
so that kind of stuff is beginning to
happen again i mean the village
carnivals village festivals
with its sharing of uh of experiences
village community life in various ways
but when it comes to the actual economic
life
of regions is still so totally dominated
by
the opportunities inherent in modern
technology
that there's this disconnect between a
local community
and its surrounding countryside and that
i think until we
get get get to grips with that it's
gonna be hard
to make relocalization of the kind that
you talk about
true reality yeah no i completely agree
i mean
we could have a to just just talk about
the role of technology that would be
fascinating because um
i'm like bucky fuller's famous quote
um if you want to change the way people
think don't tell them what to think
give them a tool the use of which will
change the way they think
um yeah that's the nice code yeah i used
this quote a number of times in a number
of settings but only
in the last few months have i realized
that
if you apply that quote to any
technology from the printing press to
the computers we're currently using to
have this conversation to
everything we use it it begins to really
unpack how insidious
technology actually pervades in all our
lives and has affected how we think
about how to create solutions how to
meet needs how to relate to people how
to relate to the world
and and i'm i'm not saying that it's all
negative but
we we seem to not be able to
step back enough to really have an
ethical conversation about what
technology is
to use when and how and particularly the
systemic understanding
of the side effects of it seemed like a
good idea at the time to have a tractor
that can
take people away from the hard work of
walking behind a animal that was pulling
a basic plow but um
we we don't think of all the side
effects that come with the the use of
these
these um technologies and but that you
know
when i moved and my wife and i moved to
our cottage
uh 44 years ago
and we bought a little tractor in order
to farm you know
make hay and all the rest of it um plow
some fields and so on um
that was a 20 horsepower tractor and
then those days that was
you know a small practice at the time
but typically that time
you had 40 40 horsepower tractors as the
norm
today 200 300 horsepower yeah
and that means far far less people
working the land even than
they did 40 years ago localization is a
wonderful concept and i mean i really
you know admire the vigor in which this
is being pursued by
so many people including yourself and
i've written about it and i've
you know that way of life is much more
local than it would have been
while we were living in london all those
years ago but certainly
aspects of local life are reviving
very actively no no doubt about it but
by and large unless we get
to grips with the economics of it as
well
the culture to to fit the bill and the
way that we would like to
well i think we've had a wonderful
wide-ranging conversation really
appreciate your time and and love to do
this again it's great to be in touch and
let's
what what are you doing now in you know
in majorca you told me that you were
trying to do a sort of adelaide type of
initiative there is that happening or
yeah i mean that what i've learned with
working at that system scale of a whole
island and a small city
is that you can't push it but you have
to be there when the opportunity arises
and i i sense that
10 years of conversations and
relationships
buildings are starting to converge just
tomorrow i'm having a conversation with
um a local friend who's put forward a
proposal called balearesvert which is um
to plan a million trees across different
places on
majorca in agroforestry productive
systems to learn
how to farm in the future as climate
change
um unfolds here in the mediterranean and
and linked that in with
will and fever's wonderful four returns
approach um that he developed with the
common land foundation
and um and local landowners around the
island and and that will
begin the conversation around what does
bioregional regeneration
at island scale look like and we have
this wonderful opportunity to do it
both marine regeneration with the
the sea between the islands and
terrestrial regeneration
and of course the opportunity and the
crisis that we're now in
with the major local economy having
collapsed
and people not quite willing yet to
admit to what extent it has collapsed
semi-permanently or will not bounce back
to the
the unsustainable and and before levels
that it was before
um i think major is
in for three four really difficult years
and where they have to let go
of um previous givens
and assumptions that that will never
change but but it
that i see a huge potential um for for
people being open
to um
rethink the future and rethink
the whole island and the islands as
potential models for exactly the kind of
conversations that
that we were just having like how do we
create alternative models of
regionalization and to what extent and
what is actually possible
and um islands are great examples of
of by regional um yeah absolutely
and what about renewables i mean are you
getting you know is
my getting serious about powering itself
renewable finally there's been a little
bit of a shift
just in the last few months as part of
the the corvette response they've
they've flagged up that they will agree
50 new solar parks around um
okay what about wind wind has always
been an
issue because of the the local bird
watching
organization is also very strongly
involved in
protecting the environment in general
and and they have
bought into this this um unfounded
belief that windmills
um kind of uh are bad for bird life
and i mean the reality
um it's so far not in conversation
um because you know i don't know how
deep the sea is but you know there are
now these floating turbines you know
i there's plenty there's plenty of
opportunities for renewables around the
balearics um
to my mind it would have to be a really
diverse um
and and more rather than creating large
wind farms
and create decentralized diverse systems
of both solar
and solar thermal spain has has the
highest
um like one of the the best
solar thermal power plant companies in
the world um
is from sevilla in southern spain so we
we we could
use concentrated solar thermal to
absolutely
some of the power plants we've got so
the short answer is i still have you in
the back of my mind
i would love to when the conditions are
right here to suggest that
you and barbara come down for some time
in mallorca and
you can be a thinker of residents and
share the adelaide examples and all
your wisdom um we'll see if i can make
it happen okay great
okay but have a great day and say hello
to your wife and
thank you so much for watching bye